
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 <channel>
   <title>Blockchains on Kishan Sagathiya</title>
   <link>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/blockchain/</link>
   <description>Recent content in Blockchains on Kishan Sagathiya</description>
   <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
   <language>en-us</language>
   <lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 16:54:39 +0530</lastBuildDate>
   
       <atom:link href="https://kishansagathiya.github.io/blockchain/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
   
     <item>
       <title>Golang Is Not Truly Opensource</title>
       <link>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/golang-is-not-truly-opensource/</link>
       <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2020 13:57:10 +0530</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/golang-is-not-truly-opensource/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;For the most of my career I have written softwares using Golang and almost all
of my code resides on the world to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a certain image of an Open Source project in my mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code for Everyone to see&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lot of people use the software&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They have a say in what happens to the project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The project attempts to explain what the code does&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The project attempts to be easily accessible and conforms to the community rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Softwares are complex and big. If I put my code on GitHub for all to see without
good documentation, it is just as bad as not putting the code in public. No one
will be able to make sense of that. Most companies do this and act as if they care
about opensource. Putting your junk software on GitHub is not open source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you build something for your specific use case and no one else needs that product,
don&amp;rsquo;t bother showing that source code to people. If Facebook has the code
for their site &lt;code&gt;facebook.com&lt;/code&gt; for all to see and all of its contributors are
employees of facebook, all the people asking for features are employees of facebook and
no other organization is building a facebook-competitor using this code, I would not
call it open source, because no one else cares for the code except themselves. It
might as well be closed source and it won&amp;rsquo;t make any difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the contributors are on either GitHub or GitLab. Using your own git platform is
basically like telling that we don&amp;rsquo;t care if we get contributors or not and we don&amp;rsquo;t
care what other software engineers think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost all of the developers of Golang are Google Employees. It is part of the google
and not a neutral foundation. They use their own git platform instead of GitHub or
GitLab. They have religiously ignore heavily demanded features from the community. It
is being developed more like an iPhone, where you think that users are dumb they don&amp;rsquo;t
know what they want. Golang is a great language, but it sure as heck not open source.
Having such a strong user base of Golang, gives them a great power and control over
the developers and indirectly the way they develop softwares. This powers can be easily
used to do good of Google rather than others.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>How to Take Advice</title>
       <link>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/how-to-take-advice/</link>
       <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jul 2020 13:59:59 +0530</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/how-to-take-advice/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;In general the rule of thumb in taking advice is &lt;code&gt;do as I do, not do as I say&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Internet is filled with successful people giving advices. Elon Musk, Peter Theil,
etc. Apply their advice in your life and you will live a miserable poor life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me break this down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of successful people thinks that world is what they have experienced. In
reality, they are all outliers. World they experience is vastly different than
any one of us experience. They are successful, so they can get away with pretty
much whatever bullshit they desire like work non-stop, or don&amp;rsquo;t go to college.
And their blind follower will somehow convince themselves whatever this
successful-but-ignorant dude is saying is the right thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When they give you advice, they are thinking that whatever worked for them
will work for you too, without realizing how big of an outlier they are. Only
data point they have considered is themselves. If not, they have also considered
some of their other successful friends who are just as ignorant of the world as
they are. Their heads are so far up their asses they have no grasp of reality
or common sense. They can&amp;rsquo;t fathom that there is any other way of thinking than
their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about this advice &lt;code&gt;don&#39;t go to college&lt;/code&gt;. First of all, people who scored
straight As in their college are telling others to not go to college. Ask one
of them to fund a company started by someone without a college degree and see
what happens? See how many fancy college grads they themselves have hired. Bryan
Caplan is an economist who devoted his life to study education system in US. He
has written a book called &lt;code&gt;The case against Education&lt;/code&gt;. He argues about how useless
higher education is, but even he agrees that on an individual level there are
great benefits of going to college. For example, having a Masters degree will
get you 10% more annual salary than an someone doing the same job without a Masters
degree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, most of these people have to secure their company&amp;rsquo;s own interest.
Everything that they say is sugar-coated to protect their organization&amp;rsquo;s interests.
For example, Elon Musk keeps talking about how AI is going to take over the world.
Ask anyone who has learn AI (think a Masters degree in AI) and he will tell you
how big of a lie it is. Some of them go even as far as saying that it will create
jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the business-person, I really respect is Shridhar Vembu. He is as honest as
a business-person can get. He describes a PhD degree as mental masterbation and he
regrets having one. I like to think the mental masterbation part to be true, but my
guess is that without that PhD it would have been quite difficult for him to even
enter the borders of USA and he would have lost a lot of business because of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a biological standpoint, greatest flattery is still imitation and people
reward imitation. That&amp;rsquo;s why college professors care so deeply about grades. That&amp;rsquo;s
why people hire from their own almamater, etc. My intution is that to be successful,
you have to conform to current stardards, regardless of how useless they are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, it is a good idea to take advice from economists than anyone who is
successful.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>Tech Recruiting</title>
       <link>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/tech-recruiting/</link>
       <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2020 14:01:19 +0530</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/tech-recruiting/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;Recruiting in tech is a very interesting problem and I feel like very few companies
have nailed this well, mostly because of nature of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recruiting Software Engineer in general is a difficult task. Grades tell you if the
person is hard-working and conformist. There is a positive co-relation between Grades
and whether you can code or not, but it is not so strong. There is a positive
co-relation between your competitive coding skills (think data structures and algorithms),
but it is still not strong, because competitive programming requires you to spend a lot
of time banging your head to solve some puzzle and relatively little time programming.
Real life software development also requires you to bang your head to fix a bug, but
it involves a lot more of reading through the documentation, searching through the
internet and reading articles. If you have written softwares before, that definitely
is a positive indication, but there is no telling how long you will take to learn things
in this new organization. So, clearly what you can show on paper is not good
enough to figure out if you can write good software, but neigher is interviewing you
for a bunch of hours.
Thus making it a very interesting problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience, most start-ups don&amp;rsquo;t have rigid hiring method, partly because they
are still learning how they should select people for their new organization. Software
Engineers that makes sense for big corps, don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily make sense for start-ups.
Start-ups optimize for skills (what can you do right now). Big corp optimize for
capabilities (what can you do six months from now, or even longer).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overtime a typical startup find a good method to hire candidates that works for them.
But soon enough, they are going to be bigger, they will be getting a lot more applications
and they would be able to invest more time in letting a talented person learn a new
skills. They will have to change their method again and they will have to optimize their
method for capabilities and elimination. In optimizing for elimination they will lose
some good candidates, but they can probably afford it and they don&amp;rsquo;t have resources to
consider all of them seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another problem for startups is that they have hire people with skills which they themselves
(members of the startup) don&amp;rsquo;t possess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone could possibly master this art of recruiting and putting people in right boxes.
May be, someday we will have an app like Uber for Engineers. You just tell the app what
what you are looking for, how many people you are looking for and it will show you a bunch
of engineers which you hire without even interviewing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>Align the Interests!</title>
       <link>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/align-the-interests/</link>
       <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jun 2020 14:05:00 +0530</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/align-the-interests/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;Any business where the interests of consumer and producer are not aligned, is
begging to be disrupted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mutual fund house is not sufficiently incentivized to grow money invested in the
fund. It is not their money. People working in finance can make more money by sales,
than making your product better. You make more money by selling your mutual fund
units than making better investment decisions using existing cash. It takes years
to determine whether a investment decision is right or not. An employee working in
a finance company wants promotion. How can the management determine which employee
is better? How can an employee impress their boss? Sales. Just sales. Interest of
Fund manager and an individual who invested in the fund are not aligned. If 50% of
the money is invested by the fund itself, investment decisions would be significantly
different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A real estate agent can make more money by selling you a shitty house at high price
than selling you a good house and lower price. They don&amp;rsquo;t have to care about customer
satisfaction, because customers are not recurring. People buy houses only few times in
their lifetime. Interests are not aligned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A university can make more money by selling you their shitty program at high price
than actually finding what will help you the most with your career. Customers are not
recurring here and it will take years to determine the true value of your education.
Interests are not aligned here. Universities are more incentivized to sell than
actually delivering customer utility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Private universities are in the same league as an investment house and real estate.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>Spineless Intelligents Will Work for Risk Taking Idiots</title>
       <link>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/spineless-intelligents-will-work-for-risk-taking-idiots/</link>
       <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jun 2020 14:03:18 +0530</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/spineless-intelligents-will-work-for-risk-taking-idiots/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;In a world full of so many opportunities, where a poor person has all the valuable
information at their disposle to make their life better, intelligent and hard-working
people are abundant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the working world, there are basically two kinds of people, enterpreneurs and
investor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enterpreneurs do all sorts of unconventional things to get users and
create hype for whatever they are doing. A significant number of them are scams,
dillusional and are trying to do things in which they have no expertise, but they
will claim to have expertise in them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investor are of two types, ex-enterpreneurs who made a lot of money and people
from fancy colleges. An enterpreneur-turned-investor who created a company in
a specific sub-industry is an expert in the product that they built and customers
of their product. Their knowledge is very much in this very specific area and
questionable in everything else. But because they became successful in that, they
somehow start thinking that they know about other things too. Very few people
try to show them the reality that they are not expert in other things, because
they are successful. They make mistakes of investing in companies  and industries
which they know very little about. They end up investing in companies than can put
on a show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A guy-from-fancy-college investor doesn&amp;rsquo;t care if his/her investment choices are
good or not, because a) it is not his money and b) 6 years from now when returns
of those investment would come he would be working at some other firm. He knows
nothing about how that AI company can different between human and cat and how
that new cryptocurrency algorithm is even valid. He is interested in investing
in companies that can create great buzz so that he can get a promotion or a better
job. They too invest in companies that can put on a show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everytime I go see what new opportunities are there in the market, I see shitty
companies about which I can tell that their product is not going to move a needle.
But I have to think about applying there, because they have got huge funding and
pay great salaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intelligent people who take calculated risks go a long way, mostly because there
are so few.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>Why Is BTech in India Four Years Long?</title>
       <link>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/why-is-btech-in-india-four-years-long/</link>
       <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 14:07:30 +0530</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/why-is-btech-in-india-four-years-long/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;An Undergraduate Engineering degree is the most popular degree in India. If you
are reading this and you are indian, there are high chances that you are an
engineer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try to remember the subjects in your Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree. Let&amp;rsquo;s try to remove
everything that was useless in that degree and see what is left.
Regardless of your engineering branch, the first year of engineering is same
for all. In most cases, there are only one or two relevant subjects to your
branch. So, out of 12 subjects in first year, you are never going to use 10
subjects. Let&amp;rsquo;s get rid of them. The last year has very few subjects. Most
students study very little and just waste their time in the last year (smoke,
drink, hike, go home, pretty much whatever tickles their fancy). Let&amp;rsquo;s get rid
of that extra time. So, you have got a curriculum that you can very conveniently
finish in 3 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a crazy idea. In UK, you have 3-years Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degrees. College
administration will try to fool you by saying things like we are promoting
interdisciplinary studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, why are our degrees 4 years long?
Because Universities in US would not accept a 3 years Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree. A huge
chunk of engineering students go to US for higher studies. Even if they don&amp;rsquo;t
have a plan they would want that option to be open. Not many BSc student go to
US for higher studies, thus most BSc programs in India are 3 years long. But
a Bachelors of Science from IISc is a 4-year long program, so that they can study
in US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why would they not accept 3 year degrees?
Because in US a Bachelors degree (both engineering and science) is 4 years long.
In most countries, prominent universities, universities where brightest students
and brightest researchers go are public universities. But in US, most prominent
universities and most universities as well are private universities. This includes
all ivy leagues (Harvard, Yale, MIT, Cornell, Brown, Dartmouth, University of
Pennsylvania), Stanford and most universities that does not have &lt;code&gt;state&lt;/code&gt; in their
name. Their main goal is to make money, just like any other private company. A
4-year program gets them tuition fee for one extra year. Accepting a students with
3-Year Bachelors program hurts the business. Now because of this, state universities
in US also has to fall in line and keep a 4-year degree, so that their students
remain eligible to study at these private university. Of course, they would never
accept that this is why they do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not just limited to Bachelors. A PhD program in US is 5 years long, while
it does not have to be. In Europe(including UK), PhD program are typically 3 years
long. Some programs are 4-years long, but that is max. A PhD student is a highly
intelligent individual who is substantially underpaid. Having a PhD student
stick around for 2 extra years, saves money on teaching and research staff. Often
advisers intentionally block doctorates, so that they can utilize their students as
cheap resources. Universities would argue that a 5-Year PhD would give you
substantial research exposure, which is true. But again, they are just trying to
fool people. A 7-year PhD program would give even more research exposure. Heck,
better yet 10-years would give even better exposure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to fix it?
Indians could have handled the situation smartly. We should have a 3-Years Bachelors
program and when a 21 year old adult(?) thinks that opportunity cost of studying at a
university that secretly invests in fossil fuels and not earning for two years is
justified they can take extra courses to finish credit-requirements to satisfy a 4-Year
degree program.
(Hint: Name of that university rhymes with &lt;code&gt;Howard&lt;/code&gt;. Also, what a dumb investment!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wasted a year in the prime of my life because of stupidity of Indian Education system
and profit-hungry private colleges and so does many other students.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>Master in AI</title>
       <link>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/master-in-ai/</link>
       <pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 14:09:44 +0530</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/master-in-ai/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;Few days ago I purchased the domain name &lt;a href=&#34;masterinai.com&#34;&gt;masterinai.com&lt;/a&gt; and launched a site
that would give people certificate saying that &lt;code&gt;You have finished the coursework equivalent to that of a masters program and you possess similar knowledge&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, education is free. If you want to learn anything, you can go online,
find free books, tutorials series, video lectures. There are even sites that
let&amp;rsquo;s you do free exercises. The education methods available online are highly
superior compared to that of your college professor and classroom learning.
This is truly great time for those who want to learn. You are not limited by
resources, but only by your willingness to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, it is not really possible to charge someone a lot for education material.
Despite this, colleges are still thriving. Despite their exuberant fees, there
is tremendous competition for getting college programs. That clearly tells that
colleges are providing something that is truly valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Colleges provide you with recognition and community. A job, a bootcamp or a
series of online courses might not remain relevant or significant enough to put
on your resume after some years. Unlike those, a college degree stays on your
resume for the rest of your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it possible to provide valuable recognition at a cheaper cost and without
having to go through thousand things that are wrong with colleges?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will try to come up with a framework to be recognised, given that you possess
the knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, say a 40 years old English Teacher wants to get a job at Google
as an AI Researcher. He cannot afford to leave his job, not earn for two years,
and pay $80,000 tuition fees. Luckily, there is an online degree option for a
much cheaper price, $30,000. But to even apply for the program, he has to write
GRE (so irrelevant), prepare a letter of motivation to do that program, find
two recommendation letters. Even, if he does that he might just get rejected,
because he doesn&amp;rsquo;t really have the relevant background. Say, he is hardworking,
self motivated and willing to finish the complete masters level coursework to
prepare him to do research in AI. How can he prove that he is as good as
someone with a masters degree and deserves that job? This the recognition
problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per the framework I am proposing, if he finishes following tasks, he should
be deemed equivalent to having a masters degree:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Say, every chapter in the coursework contains quizzes. He has to clear every
quiz.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where applicable a chapter would be accompanied with assignments. He has to
clear all assignments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A showcasable usable project in the field.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Significant contributions to a known and already in use project in the field.
The important thing here is to be able to show your individual contributions
clearly. For example you could show your GitHub Pull Requests, if the project
is on GitHub. A group project where you are not able to pin point your
contributions is as good as nothing. It is much better to have have all of your
contribution linked to each other. For example, fixing bugs or doing small issues
for an open source project does not really tell much about your abilities. Building
a whole new component from start does. If all these conditions are met such
contributions can be considered as an alternative to the project component.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publish a research paper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to show that you have done, 3 to 5, you can do it on you own. To show
that you have cleared tests and assignments, you would need some site where you
submit those things and get a proof that you cleared them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do I have to do 1 and 2? Can&amp;rsquo;t I just create a cool project, contribute to
an open source project and publish a paper? There are examples of many people
getting jobs that way.
&amp;ndash;&amp;gt; Yes, that is something that you can do. But it is not same as a
degree. Doing project or publishing a paper gets you really deep
into a topic. A degree gives you breadth as well. It gives you
a decent idea about all aspects of the main subject you are trying
to master. You can build a &lt;code&gt;personalized news&lt;/code&gt; app that utilizes
Reinforcement Learning, but that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you understand all
other subjects of AI. There is value in getting that breadth.
Having breadth benefits you in the long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A site that provides those MCQ tests, Assignments, interactive communities through
online and sometimes offline events, provides certificates for finishing the program,
categorizes students based on their abilities and performance and helps them with
getting jobs through industry relations can replace colleges.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>Income Share Agreements</title>
       <link>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/income-share-agreements/</link>
       <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 14:13:59 +0530</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/income-share-agreements/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;Income Share Agreements are an excuse for education companies and colleges to
charge a lot more money than what they truly deserve. A better way to do this
would be to charge companies when they want to hire fresh graduates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High tuition fees are unjustifiable, because knowledge has become cheap. The
internet is filled with wonderful study materials, books, videos and tutorials.
In such an environment, the marginal cost of a new study material that your
college/bootcamp/(whatever new fancy thing they like to call these days) provide is
negligible (close to zero).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Private companies are utilizing ISAs. If your ISA says, we will take x percent,
of your salary for first two years of your employment, your educators have incentives
to actually get you a great job. Which is good for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But now all these expensive universities have started using ISAs.
Because students don&amp;rsquo;t have to pay right now, they don&amp;rsquo;t realize the fact that
they are being charged way too much money. It is same as the trap of loan. If
there were no education loans, how many students would be willing to pay these
exuberant prices? Much less students. Would that make colleges/bootcamps lower
their prices? Significantly.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>Creators and Engineers</title>
       <link>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/creators-and-engineers/</link>
       <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 14:12:18 +0530</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/creators-and-engineers/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;For good or bad, you don&amp;rsquo;t need to be a Good Engineer to create a useful product.
Most users don&amp;rsquo;t know the first thing about privacy, security and optimisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is thread trending on hacker news about someone whose extension is being
removed from Google Web Store. This person has written some seriously bad code,
and is so clueless about why Google is removing their extension. His/her extension
has more than a million users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk shipped products faster by writing crappy code. He famously wanted to
use Microsoft Servers instead on Linux, because doing so would have helped them ship
things faster. Max Levchin threatened to leave if they did not use Linux Servers.
Most companies that used Microsoft servers died, they survived, because PayPal
luckily used Linux Servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t know binary trees well, you are not a good engineer. If you create
Homebrew, that doesn&amp;rsquo;t change the fact that you are not a good engineer. You are
a good creator. Engineers optimise, clean. They have keen eye for details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most startups ship things faster by writing crappy code. Fancy word for that is
&lt;code&gt;organically developed&lt;/code&gt; (read a giant hot mess). That code is a ticking time-bomb.
If people start using the thing, they eventually hire &lt;code&gt;engineers&lt;/code&gt;, who will unravel
that mess. The company survives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big companies often use &lt;code&gt;engineers&lt;/code&gt; to build new products, who will try hard to not
ship bad code. They end up shipping fewer products and even fewer useful products.
Often most of their successful products are accessories/integrated to their primary
product (built by founders). Often a lot of their successful products are built by
startups that they acquired.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>My Brain Dump to Improve Higher Education</title>
       <link>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/my-brain-dump-to-improve-higher-education/</link>
       <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2020 14:15:36 +0530</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/my-brain-dump-to-improve-higher-education/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;These are my notes when I was thinking on how can I build to a college of my dreams.
I don&amp;rsquo;t know when I will be able to do it, since&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it will definitely require funding,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it would take really long time to make a different kind of college mainstream,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;amount of money to be made are probably not justifiable with the efforts that
anyone will have to put.  I will feel as if I am doing a disservice if I try to
the society squeeze more money&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I am putting all of my raw thoughts here, so if someone with superpowers ever
gets lost on this corner of the internet, there is a tiny chance that this will
become a reality. For more context read my previous two blogs &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@kishansagathiya/faults-in-our-higher-education-system-ad68bc0abe9b&#34;&gt;Faults in our higher education system&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@kishansagathiya/and-how-to-fix-them-6372a6a49efe&#34;&gt;And how to fix them&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://kishansagathiya.github.io/pdfs/Jamooraa_Braindump.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF of Brain Dump&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>Problems With Working Remotely From India</title>
       <link>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/problems-with-working-remotely-from-india/</link>
       <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2020 14:22:44 +0530</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/problems-with-working-remotely-from-india/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;Remote work is great for so many reasons. You get to work from wherever you want,
you don’t have to commute to the office and get stuck in traffic. It is great if
you want to travel the world and work at the same time. It is great if you have
kids to take care of and parents to help at home. You don’t have to move to a
different city. And many other such wonderful things. I enjoyed my time as a remote
developer and still do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But just like everything else, it too has problems.  I will only talk about the
problems of doing remote work from India, because that’s what I am most familiar with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proof of Employment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most remote developers working for an offshore company are not officially employees
of that company. Developers charge them monthly invoices. The company cannot provide
developers monthly pay slips, form 16 or employee benefits. At my age, couldn’t care
less about employee benefits (I should though), but I do care about pay slips. For
most traditional institutions, pay slip is the proof that you have a steady source of
income. Without that you fall into the category of self-employed. You can show your
contract with the company and recurring transactions of income, but that won’t work.
Pay slips are just too straightforward  and easy for them, they just don’t want to deal
with anything else.
Try applying for a credit card without a payslip. You will either have to wait until
you file multiple Income Tax Returns or maintain good balance for a reasonable time.
And still your credit limit will be much lower than someone earning the same amount,
but has a pay slip. For my visa applications, I had to highlight multiple transactions
in my bank statements, provide certificates for my business entity, a copy of my really
long consulting contract. Which government officer wants put efforts in going through
all that? They would be happy to serve someone with a payslip and choose to avoid you
who is confusing them with so much paperwork. A huge number of Indian professionals
are first generation of office-goers in their family. They don’t have many proofs to
show their financial stability. In that way, a pay slip, I think, would matter more
than it does in other countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remote developers would need to travel offshore to meet their colleagues. I have wasted
a considerable amount of time preparing my visa applications. If I had someone to handle
that for me, I would have been a much happier developer and put more of my time in doing
software development.
As far as I know, most MNCs in Bangalore, handle visa for their employees. I can’t
expect a remote-first offshore company to do my visas for me, especially if it is small,
which almost all of them are. They don’t know how to deal with this problem any better
than you do. And honestly, doing this may be sub-optimal use of their time and it is better
spent on something else productive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Handling taxes myself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is sub-optimal use of my time. My time is best spent on software development. By now I
know a lot about taxing than what I did a year ago, more than some local CAs. Which is not
a complement on me, but a remark on many CAs.
Finding a good CA is tough. Finding the one you can trust is even tougher. I had to
cross-verify things they were saying and often times, what they were saying would be wrong.
Often instead of them giving me ideas on how to save taxes, I had to tell them and they nod
yes. One of them had this grand idea of making me pay 35% tax (30% is max tax for the highest
slab). I think I have finally found the right CA.
But given the option, I would have chosen to learn none these and would have delegated this
to someone else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Loneliness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you go to the office, you can make friends, talk to people and maintain your sanity.
Sitting at home with no one to talk to, you get bored and insane. It could make sense for
someone with the family, but that’s not the case here. A large chunk of Indian developers
are in their 20s, avoiding marriage. Plus most of them are living in metros, far away from
their hometown. So, your office circle is your primary social circle. They can try to go
back to their hometown, but that place would not have good facilities and other developer
peers.
You could try going to some coworking space, but they are simply put useless. The problem
with today’s offices is that they are so open, noisy, distracting and everyone just keep
pulling each other into their solving their problems. I would be surprised if any real work
gets done in a coworking space, because they are not optimized for productivity and
&lt;code&gt;collaboration&lt;/code&gt;.
But why do you care, you want to go there to socialize anyway. Problem is that most of the
coworking spaces are  occupied by startup teams. They have their own circle and not need to
socialize with other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unreliable Internet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of all the problems, this one can be most easily addressed. I had two wired internet
connections (Spectra and Airtel). Sadly, there was metro construction outside my society.
Most of India is developing rapidly. This is the story of almost everywhere. Construction
is going on everywhere from metros to villages. Because of that they would break cable every
few days. I have attended quite a few meetings on relatively slow wireless internet.
Interestingly, my society was inside a tech park. They surely don’t have internet outages.
Companies have separate connections that goes deeper and doesn’t get broken easily. Only if
I could get that connection for my apartment!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No office&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know complaining about not having an office is so not remote-like. This is a problem
nonetheless.
Like it or not, but staying at home and working is not easy. I have weights and ropes in
my room right next to my table, but I rarely use them. I end up doing more exercise when
I wear my shoes and get out of my house at 6 in the morning. Most human habits are based
on rituals. Going to office is a ritual that gives you a mental switch and ensures that
you will work. Waking up early is the ritual. If you do it, you are much more likely to
exercise. With a home office, it is difficult to balance work and life.
Plus, most indian households are noisy, chaotic, sudden guests and in general not a great
place to work. If you stay at home, someone will ring the doorbell, you will have to take
your dog to pee, attend the electrician, give your brother’s friend his book back and many
other small tasks just enough to stop you from long stretch of focussed work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think most of these are problems for the companies as well, since these things make their
developers less productive. And fixing them will make more developers open to remote working.
I am trying to solve some of these problems with remote91.in. Check it out and get in touch
to solve them for your company.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>Which Cryptocurrencies Will Survive</title>
       <link>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/which-cryptocurrencies-will-survive/</link>
       <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2020 14:24:27 +0530</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://kishansagathiya.github.io/posts/which-cryptocurrencies-will-survive/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;I am in the cryptocurrency/blockchain space now for about more than two years. Overtime,
I have developed a hypothesis of my own about what it will take to make a cryptocurrency
successful in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand this we have to realize that cryptocurrencies are directly opposite to the
government. Much of the power that the government gets is from its ability to control the
money, collect taxes, being able to spend that money in different sectors as government feels
appropriate. If a cryptocurrency replaces currency of the government (fiat currency), that
shifts all the power from the government to people who control that cryptocurrency (developers,
miners, users). In the resulting powerless government, you have a society with no order and
everything goes haywire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To tackle economic problems such as unemployment and inflation, government has primarily
two ways, fiscal policy (adjust taxation and government spending, usually done by the goverment
department) and monetary policy (adjust money supply and interest rates, usually done by the
central bank). There is clearly no way to implement monetary policy in cryptocurrency world
because of its fundamental virtue (decentralization). In an imaginary world full of honest
taxpayers, government can implement fiscal policy, but clearly that will never happen. Some
countries have introduced negative tax rates to increase business and employment. That can&amp;rsquo;t
happen if government does not control the currency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am convinced that cryptocurrencies are here to stay, but most likely they won&amp;rsquo;t replace fiat
currencies or central banks, but will replace gold and store credits. If cryptocurrencies
replace central banks, that society and economy will be controlled by people controlling those
cryptocurrencies (rich people), and thus would be worse than what we have now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that bit of context, these are the things I think are needed for a cryptocurrency to
replace fiat currencies&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can be used even if it can&amp;rsquo;t be traded with fiat currencies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most cryptocurrencies today will see a sharp decline in their value if they cannot be traded with
fiat currencies, which means their value still comes from fiat currencies and are merely gambles.
Governments allow cryptocurrencies until they don&amp;rsquo;t see a real threat from them, which is when their
value comes from fiat or they can control and monitor transactions by rules and regulations (government
can take away the value whenever they want). One way to do this is obviously having the trust of
users. One more way is to codify it in such a way that it can be traded for a valuable digital resource
(computation, storage, network).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maintained by developers which are unknown&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the group that maintains source code of the cryptocurrency is public, the government can control
them and influence their decisions either by bringing forward new regulations or forcefully.
Controlling those developers translates to controlling the currency. Also, it would be nice if no
single developer has a cult like following and many developers contribute relatively equally. It is
really rare for that to happen, that too on its own. If a cryptocurrency source code and technology
is maintained by group is publicly known and concentrated in country X, it a national security threat
for a country Y where that particular cryptocurrency is getting popular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Users can remain anonymous&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That way it remains usable even if banned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solid protocol with bug-free implementation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is obvious. Users will lose money because of bugs in implementation or loopholes in the
protocol and will likely not trust again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decentralized way to download the client&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are ways to do this, but I am not sure if it is possible or easy with the internet as it is
today. Take inspirations from IPNS and DNS-Links. Different peers would have different versions
of client. Match client copies of version that you want and download the most common one. Something
that can be downloaded from bitcoin.org or ethereum.org still seems pretty centralized to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cryptocurrencies that matches most with above, are generally popular for illegal activities,
funding crimes, black money etc. So, this seems like a good rule of thumb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think someone who wants to make a strong cryptocurreny can learn a lot from torrents and its
community. It is an amazing technology where developers are not so famous, there are multiple clients,
multiple torrent link providers, multiple seeder and leechers etc. It is decentralized in many ways.
It has survived despite government bans. Domain names got banned, but there are many torrent-listing
sites with different domains and now there are sites that provide lists of active torrent-listing
sites. Regardless of whether you like or dislike torrents because of its legality, it provides a
great model for distributed software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most cryptocurrencies can be divided into four categories based on how many boxes it ticks
from above listed properties (most boxes to least)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rupee-alternative&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gold-alternative&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Store credits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gamble&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gamble currencies will disappear eventually. Store credits stay as long as the store stands. Gold is
timeless (but which one?). Rupee-alternative is hopefully never happening.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     </item>
   
 </channel>
</rss>
